Millions of personal trainers
are getting a bum fucking deal.
And what that means
is you think the gym
that you're working for is
providing a safe,
nurturing environment for you,
but they're robbing you in broad
daylight. And in this video,
I'm going to break down exactly why you
need to leave,
become more independent,
and reap the rewards of working for
yourself.
Even Declan here,
you worked for a gym in the city,
qualified PT, and you didn't
have to pay rent, did you, Declan?
And neither do a lot of people watching
this
video. So what do you call it? Free rent.
But it's not free, is it, Declan? Why
is it not free, Declan?
Because they take a fat cut.
What do they take? 50%. Do you know what?
That's more than the top tax bracket
worldwide.
In Australia, 47%. In the UK, 45%.
You have
to earn a substantial amount of money
before you get anywhere near that tax
bracket. How old were you when you
were working there? 23.
Were you in the top threshold for tax,
Declan? No. And what were they taking?
Too much. I get it.
When you look at the rent gyms
charge to be self-employed, AKA,
I pay you money, you let me use the
gym floor, it can seem really expensive.
For a start,
I'm going to steelman the argument for the
gyms.
Gym equipment is expensive.
Like even here, a red bumper plate,
it's like
$200. Barbells are expensive. $800 for
a barbell.
So when you think about equipments,
leg press, insurance, air con,
showers,
and even making sure there's toilet roll
in the toilet so that your client
can wipe their ass,
it's not a terrible deal.
Now, last time I made this video,
I went into what we call fag
packet maths. And in the UK,
when we say fag, we mean cigarette.
And sometimes when you do a deal with
someone, rough calculations.
There'll be a bit of that today,
but I'm also going to use my uncle who's
an
accountant, and that is Uncle ChatGPT.
So let's do a scenario.
You're in the United Kingdom.
You're working for a gym like David Lloyd.
Allegedly,
David Lloyd take 50% of what you charge
for free
rent. So let's work this out. My friend
is a personal trainer.
They work at a gym,
which we will call David Lloyd.
They work 25 hours a week doing coaching.
They charge £50 an hour.
David Lloyd take 50%
of every penny they earn.
I'm pretty sure they even take VAT in the
UK, but
we're not going to get too complex.
Scenario one,
we're going to call it the bum deal.
If I'm charging £50 a session,
but I have to give half to the gym, so
25 hours, £25, 52 weeks a year,
32,500. Now, out of this amount, the first
12,570 is tax-free.
Then the remaining amount would be taxed
at
20% because of the amount
that we earn a year,
we don't move into that next
tax bracket. Minus National Insurance,
your income tax for the year is
about, give or take, 4,000.
National Insurance, you pay
6,318 tax. And you're probably thinking,
"That's not a bad tax bill.
I'm pretty happy where I am.
I'm happy to work for the gym.
Yeah, they're taking a cut,
but they're keeping my costs out." After
tax, you're
going to take home about £26,000,
2,177 a month.
Now,
this is the most important figure
that we need.
My friend wants to leave the gym to do
their own thing.
They are worried they would have to pay
extortionate rent.
Can't spell.
Three times number one bestselling author,
can't spell. Nailed it.
In other facilities on a monthly basis for
the privilege of
being able to run their own business on
the gym floor.
From a UK tax perspective, scenario one,
working for
David Lloyd, I assume they would be PAYE,
which pays you earn.
So the gym paid you a salary every week.
They're like, "Declan,
you did 20 sessions, you get this."
And it was a payslip.
Always got to say thank you to AI.
All right? I'm just saying,
they're listening.
They know. And when the robots take over,
they're going to be like, "I remember
who said please and thank you." Scenario
two is where you're going to have to be
brave.
You're going to have to go out on a limb.
You're going to have to go into the big,
wide world of not having a gym look after
you for free. What does that look like?
So we still charge the same £50.
We can do 25 hours a week. It's 1,250.
Per year, 65K.
Already, that's starting to look good.
But I know what you're thinking.
I'm going to have to pay loads in rent.
So what do you think
is an acceptable amount of rent to pay a
gym?
Let's go halfway between London
and prices further out,
£700 per month, which can seem like a lot.
It's a scary amount. £700.
That could be more than your mortgage
or the amount of rent that you pay in your
home. 12 months a year,
it's nearly £9,000 a year just in rent.
Not even for your home, but for the gym.
Now, there's something unique,
this cost here,
which I don't think a lot of people
take into account. This
is deductible because it is a cost that is
exclusively and wholly for your business.
If you didn't have a business
that operated in the gym,
you wouldn't be given that.
And again, this is not financial advice.
I'm just a moron trying to make a point.
And even if my maths isn't right,
you could talk to an accountant
and come to a
similar conclusion. Now, there
are other things that are also deductible.
For instance, even right now, this board,
this table, the clever thing that's
holding the camera up there,
even all the equipment that's holding the
camera
there,
and even the young lad behind the camera
are all expenses
just for my business.
If my business doesn't exist,
I have no need for these
things.
They do not have a part in my personal
life.
So let's say another £1,600 a year in
those expenses.
Maybe a camera, maybe a tripod,
maybe expensive wireless
microphones I keep telling you to buy.
Meaning that each year you
are pissing away £10,000 in just
expenses, which can sound scary.
But remember that 65,000
that you're earning
a year.
We now get to minus £10,000 a year in
legitimate expenses,
which reduces your taxable income to
55,000.
So the first 12,000 is free.
Then we got the 20%, so we
are obviously reducing that
from that. So we go 20% on 37,700,
which is about
7,000 in tax.
Then we actually move into the higher
rate, which is 40%,
which is an additional 1,892. Now,
keep in mind, even if I have made
some mistakes here through not being an
accountant, I've used the same formula
for both scenarios. So your total tax
is going to be
9,432. So minus tax, minus National
Insurance, your take-home pay is 41,905,
which means
your monthly take-home, 3,492.
And just to make this idiot-proof,
working for the gym
and being protected
and them taking half of what you earn,
£503 a week. Going solo, £807 a
week. Annual income, 26,120. You
are better
off nearly £16,000 a year being
self-employed.
You gain full financial independence
Because although the gym
is providing something for free,
it's not free.
When you operate the business
and you take full control of the expenses,
you have
better control over your pricing,
your scheduling, your branding.
Allegedly,
David Lloyd won't let you do coaching
online, and David Lloyd in
the UK will stop you from building an
online brand, calling it a conflict of
interest. Now,
although some of you in the current model
you're in
might get some paid leave or dental
or health insurance.
For £15,000, £16,000 a year,
you could do those things yourself.
And some of you in the UK work in a pure
gym, and you do a certain amount of hours
for the gym for free to get free rent,
but it's not free.
If you deduct the amount it would cost you
to pay them rent by the amount of hours
you're doing, some of you
are earning under minimum wage.
There is no such thing as free rent.
There is no such thing as a good deal.
In almost every single scenario, you
are better off taking the money
yourself and paying the expenses of
renting a facility.
You are better off running your own
business, having your own business
expenses,
than getting paid as an employee of the
gym and being able to keep a
fraction of what you earn. Coaches
that run their own businesses,
every year we run
an IFS events,
get to expense their travel to Ibiza,
their tickets for the event,
even some meals for eating out.
One of the beautiful things of having a
job where
you can be self-employed is
that you get to leverage some of these
incredible
benefits. Of course, there
is the risk that your clients will cancel,
and at
Christmas,
no one will want to do business with you.
But it's imperative
that you work out the maths on your own
financial scenario and
situation. Declan,
did you ever do the maths on your
situation to figure out if
you'd be financially better off doing it
yourself?
No,
because it wouldn't be in the gym's best
interest for you to be thinking like
that.
I want you to have the freedom to be able
to break away from the gym that
you're in,
and the way you're going to be able to do
that is you will need to make
good, engaging content.
So rather than you having to walk the
floor to get clients,
they come to you. Now,
I sell the Short-Form Content Mastery
course that's $99, but
in the description,
I also have a Personal Trainer PT Starter
Pack
course,
and I'm going to be doing both of these
for $99.
Utilizing content and the strategy
that I put forward to build your PT
business,
you can break away from the confinement of
the gyms that you currently work for,
which means you get to keep more of your
own money. And here's the crazy thing.
I'm not asking you to work more hours.
I'm asking you to do the exact same amount
of work you're doing now, but get paid
much better because of it. So check
that out,
the link in the description below.
And fuck these gyms that
are giving you a bum deal.
They don't care about you.
The average personal training session
nearly 20 years ago was £30
an hour.
There's no way in 2025 anyone should be
getting
£27 an hour when the gym is taking 60.
That is a piss take. And
if you're still not convinced
that I'm the person to take
your fitness business to the next level,
then check out this video here where I
roast four different fitness businesses,
and I do not hold back.
And there are some discrepancies with
their approaches.
And the worst part
is some of these guys make good money.
Check this out.